so the purpose of this uh three evening
class this is the final evening of the
three evenings
um we were talking about how nice it
would be if uh we were capable of loving
every person we saw on the street in New
York right so this was our goal uh for
this class then uh we
described uh a higher kind of love and
an experience of love that comes when
the heart chakra opens and uh in that
experience uh something strange happens
your mind is released to its full
capacity and then you have the ability
to
see the faces of many people at the same
time and then I was trying to get you to
appreciate how many faces okay so uh
normally when you look at when I look at
you I have to look one by one you know
if I want to see everyone's face I have
to
scan uh my eyes across the room and and
then I can see people's faces one by one
uh if you are able to open up the heart
chakra uh then what we said is you would
have an experience where you could see
more than one person's face at the same
time uh and I don't mean in a crowd I
mean each face is full head shot
uh and and you see each of them as if
they were stocked one behind the other
but you see them all at the same time
okay you don't have to go through the
stack one by one you see every face in
the stock of papers at the same time
your mind has the capacity to see the
faces of many people at the same time
and then we said uh actually when it
happens to you when you're able to open
the heart
chakra when you have that experience uh
you'll find that the number of faces is
all the faces of the people in the world
okay so all
the faces of all the people in the world
you're able to see at the same moment
okay in a
single minute of time you see all the
faces of all the people in the world and
then we said it was more than that you
can see the faces of all the creatures
also
from you know whales and
and birds and cows down to all the faces
in each square inch of sea water in the
entire ocean okay tiny creatures you can
see all of their faces at the same time
so try to
imagine uh a state of
meditation in which you can see the
faces of every single living creature in
this
world and then multiply at times all the
worlds there are are in the universe
okay and they're countless uh there is
no end to to the worlds and there is no
end to the to the beings who live on
those worlds so try to imagine in a
meditation with your eyes closed you're
able to see the faces of every single
living creature on every world at the
same time you have your mind has this
capacity okay if you were able to open
the heart chakra you you would have this
experience okay we've been talking about
that and not just see their faces but
love them so have a deep love for each
of them a deep affection and and love
for each of the faces you see countless
faces and then a feeling like a mother
for their child and you at the moment
that you see their faces you have a
feeling of uh profound love for each one
of them like the deepest love you've
ever felt in this life for a single
person but during the opening of the
heart chakra you're able to feel this
love for all of them
equally and then there's a cool uh what
do you call it Dena there's a happy
ending to The Experience you
uh right after that you you are able to
see the future because the heart chakra
is open
then your perception of time is not
limited as long as the heart chakra is
closed you have to take life in little
10c
chunks I I call it living in a closet
you know so you are forced right now to
take
your life in in moments that follow each
other like this you know uh when the
heart chakra opens you're not limited
that way and and you can be aware of the
present moment but at the same time you
can be aware of things that will happen
many years from now hundreds of years
from now and you see them directly okay
so you're not limited
in in how many things you can see at the
same time and you're also not limited in
time itself you can see at the same
moment the faces of those people and you
can also see the day in which you will
take care of each of them okay you will
see a day
in which you will have the capacity to
take care of each of them personally
okay at the same time and that's so we
were trying to get that to happen the
purpose of this three days of classes
was uh can can I give you some kind of
practice that you can try and and that
would bring on that experience that you
would have that experience I think you
can imagine that if you had that
experience once
in your life it would change everything
about your life you wouldn't you
wouldn't be at all like you are now okay
if you haven't had that experience so if
you just could bring on this experience
for 5 minutes right then it would change
everything about your life I I don't
think it would be possible to be very
unhappy again ever because you've seen
all the creatures of the of all the
worlds and you have seen the day that
you will take care of each of them
personally and taking care of one person
makes you really happy okay taking care
of
a infinite numbers of beings at the same
time is is happiness that is happiness
okay to to do that to see that I'm going
to do that uh would change your life
forever you would never be the same it
would be very difficult to be unhappy I
think you could manage it but uh it
would be okay you're just uh your whole
life would would be fulfilled and you
wouldn't really need much more in your
life you would be contented and and
completely happy with the knowledge that
you will care for countless beings
directly personally each one and uh so
the point of this class was could could
we discuss ways of opening the heart
chakra how could we open the heart
chakra right so to towards that goal we
we yesterday discussed
the what the heart chakra looks like
okay uh what
the process what
the uh thing called the heart chakra
looks like you see and all the parts of
it and uh what what it looks like how it
came to be in the womb when you were no
more than but half an inch big okay you
were actually a tube of
sauce okay uh in the first month of in
the womb and then we said uh eight
channels uh form within the first month
uh inside the mother's womb okay and and
we said there's one main Channel called
sushumna right starts here goes under
the skull comes out from under the skull
here travels in front of the spine comes
down to the groin little pieces split
off down the legs but the main uh
sushumna terminates at the end of the
sexual organ in both a man and a
woman then even in the first month in
the womb you have a central channel it's
about this long okay and it's very
skinny all right uh then uh even in that
time you have a left and right channel
okay in an adult they they terminate
here which created
your nostrils which is why you don't go
around with one big
nostril okay and then it's good right I
don't know why it's more attractive okay
probably if we all had one we we would
be happy I don't know but uh then these
two side channels come up they cross
over the central Channel under the skull
here creating the UT chakra right the
chakra of the forehead then they
continue under the skull alongside the
central channel the sushumna and they
cross again creating a
knot uh at the tip of the head and then
they create a knot at the base of the
neck by the way the large bones of the
body form around those knots that's why
your this big bone is here called your
skull and that's why you have a C7 there
is this C7 right and okay and it creates
the bones of your spine your vertebrae
there's another not cross
over the two side channels cross over
three times behind the heart okay they
cross over and choke the central channel
uh three times at the
heart in a in a fetus in the womb uh
when The Prana is blocked at the area
that will be the heart by the two side
channels which do exist at that time
okay uh they create uh a buildup of
Prana at the in the area that will be
the heart and then uh we said four
channels break out of the side
horizontally right as if uh a garden
hose was splitting open from the
pressure of the water because Prana
cannot move because the Ida and the
pingala the two side channels are
choking the heart Channel Prana cannot
pass up the central Channel it cannot
pass down the central channel so then
builds up four channels break out uh
first to the east right to the front of
the body then to the south then to the
west then to the north uh four channels
break out of the heart so so far we have
seven
channels uh in the fetus of the fetus at
the heart and then we said there was a
sort of an auxiliary channel that comes
up the central
channel uh which is an attempt by the
body to carry The Prana which was
blocked okay so then that's called the
DU in tibetan it's
a the demon woman who obstructs the body
something like that but it contributes
to the blockage of PR at the heart so
when you are in the fetus when you are
in the womb then these eight channels
form
first uh and then we said something cool
last night we said
um when we we we kind of outlined what
happened when Prana travels through each
of the the channels right when Prana is
traveling through the middle channel the
Suna then you feel contented you feel
happy you have a high degree of
knowledge and
understanding and you have a high degree
of compassion okay when you can get any
kind of Prana into the central Channel
then you have these elevated feelings
and elevated perceptions right uh and we
said that in a normal person um uh we
say in in the scripture that normal
person means non Yogi they say in a non-
yogi in a person who doesn't understand
yoga The Prana only moves to the central
channel in under two circumstances one
is
death uh at which time the knots
released by Nature by the nature of
karma the knots uh around the heart and
the other centers they release and then
Prana enters the central Channel and you
do have an experience of what we call
clear light as you pass onto your next
birth you have a brief
experience but you are too it's too
chaotic and you can't you can't use it
okay you you can't use it to see every
living being or something like that you
have a brief uh flash of inside and then
you're on to your next body
okay and during the act of sex so during
during orgasm then some Prana travels
through the central Channel and then the
channel locks up again maybe worse than
before okay so uh in a normal
person uh Prana travels through this
channel of knowledge and contentment and
love only rarely
okay when you feel uh angry
upset uh then then Prana is moving
through the right hand Channel pingala
and it it expands that channel it gets f
and then that twist around the heart
gets fatter and it chokes the heart
worse it chokes the central Channel
worse the more Angry you get the more
impossible it is to put Prana into the
central Channel you see because you have
a limited amount of Prana it's a closed
system uh if you get upset Prana flows
out of the central channel into the
right hand channel right hand channel
gets fat like a balloon and then it
chokes the central Channel you see uh if
you and then we said um I like to call
it the Starbucks channel on the left
side the ID okay it's not bad to go to
Starbucks and have something but on your
third hot
chocolate uh Prana is Flowing out of the
central Channel when you feel contented
you had a couple sips of hot chocolate
it was a reasonable
pleasure uh you The Prana is flowing in
the central Channel okay when you get
greedy and then you want more and more
then Prana starts to leak out into the
left hand Channel ID then that channel
expands the central Channel shrinks the
knot gets bigger and then then again you
you can't think straight when you're
under the influence of your third hot
chocolate or being mad at your boyfriend
uh you can't think straight physically
there's a physical reason you can't
think straight the The Prana cannot
travel through the sushumna at that time
so we said there are eight channels that
form in the area that will be the heart
even in the womb and then you can get
you get some kind of
appreciation for the problem okay the
problem is as old as you are okay the
heart chakra has been choked uh since
the first days of your existence inside
your mother's wom okay and it's been
that way ever since all right um so what
I that's an introduction of what we've
done before uh today we want to talk
more about ways of opening uh the heart
chakra okay more more methods of opening
the heart chakra we said uh say Chang
CH
so we said you can use inner methods or
you can use outer methods inner method
would be the seven step meditation on
compassion which you learned yesterday
long time ago
uh and then slowly chip away at the knot
Around Your Heart by doing this
meditation okay did you who did you see
last night on 86
Street we saw
Margie we saw we saw a friend who who
who' you
see
huh who saw who go I saw someone I
walked out after you yeah and I looked
to the right and I saw the back of a man
and then I looked back at you say do you
think this is
him I as politely as I could
followed I have some people like
that down thir Avenue and jwalk and I
tried to jwalk but back farther yeah
yeah good you know we went into a store
following store and I got to see his
face and he got to the counter and he
said where's my
sandwich and then I saw his happy face
okay cool and then I went out to the
store out of the store and waited at one
of the
exits he'll come out this exit and one
of my friends had given me a flower yeah
at the end of class so he came out that
exit and I said do you like
flowers and he gave it to me he said I'm
going to go play the
lottery
so yesterday we were having a class on
stalking
and uh now the idea yesterday was that
uh in the course of the meditation you
uh you reflect on how if I've been here
countless times then everyone has been
everything to me meaning everyone I ever
me has been my mother has risked their
life to give me life and then last night
we had a home assignment which was to go
out and the first person we ran into we
try to imagine this person has been my
mother countless times so she ran into
that man uh ours was easier we had
Margie but
anyway so try to do that uh meditation
that that works from the inside right
that works on thought it works on the
principle in tibetan called L say
Lupa which means that uh your thoughts
right on your Prana when The Prana moves
through the body then thought moves and
this is the place where mind and body
meet okay mind is ineffable mind cannot
be weighed you could blow up you could
ignite what do you call set off a
nuclear device right here where Andy is
sitting okay and and then nothing would
happen to the minds in the room just the
bodies would be incinerated but the
minds cannot be affected by physical
matter they are they are ineffable they
have no weight uh but there is a place
where mind and body meet which is sort
of miraculous and that's that's where
Prana provides the basis for the motion
of thought when Prana moves thought
moves okay so you can direct Prana with
your thoughts or you can direct your
thoughts with your Prana and in this
system you do both okay you try to do
both right you move Prana to improve
your thoughts and then you use
meditation to move your PR okay we do
both both so the meditation would be an
inner method of of moving Prana okay
thinking about how people have been your
mother countless
times uh and then on the outside you
might do uh a specially design yoga
series uh and we'll talk about it today
we'll talk about a typical series that
was designed to open the heart chakra
okay so in in this system uh you would
do both you would work with a meditation
on the inside from the inside to open
the heart chakra and then you would work
with the ASA yoga from the outside to
open the heart
chakra and again the purpose of opening
the heart chakra is to have that
experience of Love uh which is really I
don't know if you want to call it love I
call it ultimate love in the reading
because I couldn't think of another word
to say it's kind of corny right it's not
it's not very helpful I think but it you
understand what I mean uh seeing the
faces of countless beings
it involves so many other things you see
their faces you love them and you know
you will take care of them and you see
all those things directly okay that's a
different kind of love in in in Buddhism
it's called bodh but I think you could
call it ultimate love as long as you're
aware it has those three parts to it
right you see all them you love all of
them and you perceive how you will take
care of each of them
okay so today we're going to go further
into the physical structure of the
channels uh which will help us
understand how to open them okay I
thought first we would do a meditation
okay so you ready this is a med I'll
teach you first part of a meditation uh
early in the class and then at the end
of the class we'll do a a meditation
that I would like you to try to continue
for the next few months okay that will
help you open your heart chakra
okay
please try to stay very very uh still
during the meditation if you'd like to
turn your cell phone off you could do it
now before the
meditation
okay
okay okay relax into your
seat is the air conditioning cranked up
yeah it's as far as it goes yeah okay
all
right try to stay completely still
nothing
moving
please focus on your forehead the
muscles of your forehead relax your
forehead relax any tension in your
forehead
relax the corners of your
mouth
tighten your abdomen slightly just very
slightly little tension in abdominal
muscles which releases to your lower
back and helps The Prana flow through
the central
Channel
check your eyelids the muscles in your
eyelids release the muscles of your
eyelids
then slowly start to lengthen the
exhales until you feel
relaxed
bring the mind in away from the air
conditioning noise in the room the
lights of the room and bring the Mind
towards the
breath
fix the mind on the breath
now hold the breath with your
mind we'll go through the traditional
preparation for
meditation first we always ask our heart
teacher to come to the room who whoever
it may be whoever historical person or
your own teacher in this life your own
the one you feel closest
to it could be an
imaginary heart teacher your your
personal teacher please bring them to
the room and have them sit before you
feel the warmth emanating from their
body their knees are touching your
knees hear the rustle of their
breath smell the fragrance from their
skin
then we traditionally the next step is
to make an offering to our teacher you
can imagine a
flower or a piece of incense or glass of
water but what they really enjoy is if
you
recall some small
success in your personal practice in the
last few days maybe you started to get
angry but you stopped or you started to
reach for another can of Pringles but
you stopped
or uh you took the time to speak kindly
to someone
offer a specific very specific small
success in the last few days to your
heart
teacher
e next step is to think
of mistake you've made in the last day
or two something you lost your
temper or you lost control of your
mind thought something you shouldn't
have thought or said something
unkind and try to remember a specific
thing and then make your
teacher a promise that you'll try not to
do it
tomorrow now think of something you did
good in the last few days a different
thing from what you
offered and present this goodness to
your teacher tell your teacher in your
mind offer it to them something you did
well some
kindness
then a a kindness that you saw someone
else do today what was the nicest thing
you saw anyone do today and then offer
that to your
teacher
then Imagine the One quality that you
would like to develop in your life say
in the next few weeks or months and
something about yourself you'd like to
change
improve try very hard to imagine
yourself at the end of a few
months possessing the quality that you
would like to
have in my case it's like cheerfulness
or something so
then I I try to picture myself a month
from now more cheerful and accepting
than I am today
and then ask your teacher to help
you become
that
then finally ask your the last
preparation for meditation traditional
preparation is to ask your heart teacher
to stay close even when you're not aware
of them that they should guide your
heart uh sort of steer you helped steer
you in the right direction to throughout
the day emotionally and
spiritually influence us even when we're
not aware of
it
then please come back to your breath
Focus lightly comfortably happily on
your breath no strain don't crease your
forehead nice
relaxed comfortable awareness of your
breath
lengthen the exhale of the
breath the in inhale we'll take care of
it now I'd like you to add
a mantra beginning of a
mantra on the out breath please uh
imagine that you are hearing and in your
mind you are saying the two sounds om a
so on the
exhale there'll be a om
a and then there's a silence as the
breath
pauses and then silence as the inhale
occurs om ah on the
exhale silence during the pause between
the exhale and the
inhale and then silence silence during
the
inhale
now on the inhale I would like you to
say a piece of a mantra called
H H so on the exhale
om then there's a silence during the
pause while the breath is stilled and
then on the inhale
h on the
exhale a short
silence in the pause between the exhale
and inhale and then hung on the
inhale which means you have to pause
after the
exhale before you take the inhale
slightly very
slightly on the exhale
pause h on the inhale
om on
exhale pause while the breath
reverses and then h on the
inhale
last part of this practice during the
pause between the exhale and inhale
after you have said
om but before you say h on the inhale
during the pause between the exhale and
the inhale please say the name of your
heart teacher quietly in your mind you
can shorten if it's a too long okay you
can do part of their
name so on the
exhale whisper your heart teacher's name
short part of their
name and then hung on the inhale and
then continue like that this is a mantra
based on the name of your heart teacher
which is said to be the most powerful of
all
mantras
on the exhale om on the
exhale whisper your teacher's name and
your mind on the
pause and then whom on the
inhale
for
then stop the Mantra and just breathe
watch your breath stop the
mantra
dedicate the Good Karma you just did
to seeing all the people in the world
and serving
them and then slowly come back to this
room okay and stretch and
rustle
for
so in our tradition uh this is the
highest Mantra everybody like to have a
mantra right and
uh this in our tradition this is the
highest Mantra you can have which is uh
you say
Omar and then you quietly say your heart
teacher's
name and then you put H at the end okay
it's not it's not wh okay it's h with a
NG H
say
all right and then you have a mantra
okay and this is supposed to be the this
is the highest Mantra that you can
have so I'd like to go a little bit more
into uh the structure of the heart
chakra and then you can understand why
you have those experiences when it opens
okay we said there were four channels
coming off the side of the heart
chakra even in the
womb what do those channels carry they
carry Prana right but what kind of
Prana the elements yeah relates to the
elements
okay uh the
four they're not really elements right
they're more like energies right so
Earth element is the fact that things
can hold together and not fall
apart uh very useful to have in your
body otherwise your body would fall
apart okay chew is fluidity the the
principle the
mechanics that things can be liquid and
slow uh May is the warmth temperature of
all things whether they're cold or hot
their temperature is the is the is the
element of fire okay it's it's necessary
for Life must be some heat in the in
anything for there to be life and
then CH
Prana V wind the fact that things move
for example your
blood uh has to have wind elements so
these are
not some oldfashioned idea about dirt in
your in your body or water in your body
or like that they are Elemental forces
uh which create the outer world around
you they create the movement of the
planets and they create the movement of
blood within your own body okay uh then
we said that the heart the four channels
of the heart chakra split again right
the one going to New York we're standing
in Kansas we're looking in the direct
we're facing New York right
traditionally in in Asia the front of
the body is the East right so you're
facing New York you're standing in
Kansas then the Eastern Channel splits
to the South South Florida Southeast
right that that channels another Channel
splits off like this okay so that
channel is going straight but then
another one splits off away from the
heart chakra it's not at the heart
chakra away from the heart chakra it
splits off another one towards Florida
okay then from the southern Channel
splits off another one to go to Arizona
then California has one right the
Western Channel and it splits to Oregon
or whatever and then the left hand
channel is Canada north and it it splits
off towards Maine okay so you have uh
eight channels splitting off of the
heart they don't split at the heart they
split a little bit away from the heart
inside of those four channels of the
ordinal Direction Southeast Southwest
Northwest Northeast inside of their
travels Prana which facilitates your
awareness of the objects of the world
okay when you smell something when you
see something when you feel something
it's
transmitted uh Through The Prana of
those four channels okay so you can say
even in a child in the womb
they are capable of perceiving the world
because the four primary channels of the
heart are carrying the very energies
which cause all of
creation for them and then the channels
which split off of them are are
transmitting your awareness of all of
creation within the child's channels in
the first month of the womb is contained
the universe and the capacity to to
sense the universe okay that's cool
right all right
uh that's where we left off okay now we
got to talk about uh The Prana itself
okay The Prana itself so there's Prana
moving throughout your
body it's a subtle energy it is physical
I've seen people say it's not physical
it is physical okay it's a subtle
physical energy it's similar to light
you can't grab light there's light
coming from the light bulb to my face
but I can't I can't grab it right it's a
subtle physical force and Prana is like
that okay and it carries the mind the
Mind rides on that subtle uh thoughts
ride on that subtle physical Force okay
and The Prana moves throughout the body
uh in channels called nadis
right then sometimes your body got to do
something okay like poop all right okay
or talk like that all right like
sometimes your body needs
to function your body has to do
something right and then uh through
Karma because of your karma the random
Pros moving through out your body will
gather together they'll team up to
perform a function okay so like when
you're in the bathroom right and you
like really concentrating and you go
like that when you go like that then all
the Pras collect down here all the a lot
of The Prana of the body collects down
in the lower half of the body and it
pushes okay so that's called uh well
let's do them in order okay
uh when Prana collects together to
perform a function we give it a
different name which is a Val okay so
Val means uh
a wind V means wind in Sanskrit but it's
a collection of Prana it's a gathering
of Prana in a selected area of the body
to perform a necessary function for the
continued life of the body okay and
that's called a value and there are five
Vos in tibetan there's a problem uh V is
translated as L and Prana is translated
as l so you never know if they're
talking about a Prana or V which is very
frustrating and it's a problem uh with
with Tibetan you have to understand
which one they're talking about okay so
we're going to talk about the five
Vos the five functional Gatherings of
Prana in the body and they develop in
the body in the first five months of
gestation okay so you can say that the
stages of the growth of the fetus in the
womb are in fact created by the
appearance the gradual appearance of the
values one by one okay so in the for
example in the immediately after you
cross
over from your previous
life uh into the womb immediately after
conception immediately after the sperm
meets the egg then already uh the we
call pravus say in tibetan
say in Sanskrit it's called Prana which
is already confusing cuz that Prana
doesn't mean the general Prana okay
Prana doesn't mean Prana okay pravu
means uh a a wind which is located in
the upper part of the body chest area
and uh it forms first uh immediately
after there's a continuation of Prana
from your previous life you never
completely go mental
between lives okay you lose your body
but you don't lose your subtle body okay
there's still a little Prana flowing
even between lives and then that flow of
of Prana between lives manifests within
the first few minutes of conception as
the pr
okay in tiet they say uh the function of
pranav is to maintain life itself okay
Prana
inban is called in that case it's called
sock which means life okay you would say
Aus in in Sanskrit like ayurveda okay
so the per the function of that first
collection of Prana in the body is to
maintain life itself it also helps to
draw the other winds to the senses to
the sense organs okay these are the two
functions of pranav in the upper part of
the body
the in the second month Prav triggers
upav say
upav so up means downward Tibetan call
telom say Tel Tel t means downhill cell
means uh clears clears it away clears
clears what uh feces
urine uh
Menses uh semen during ejaculation uh
children during childbirth okay when you
have to push something out
down uh the product collects together
what brings the product
together your desire to poop or whatever
okay when mind moves theana you see
that's why you got to
concentrate okay all right now I mean
somebody's banging on the door you have
problem right it's hard to to push so
your mind you think I want to poop and
then your mind has a a wish a desire and
then that desire gathers The Prana
together in the lower half of the body
and it pushes and it eliminates things
from the body okay and that's the second
uh value to form in the body during the
second month it is triggered by the
first wind in the body which is the life
wind the the the wind which holds life
okay sustains life okay that's a p of
uh third one is called uh S V say
s and that means like a equal and it's
called the equal wind okay it has to do
with
digestion uh it digests food and it
allows the body to separate the function
of digestion is to separate waste from
what's called Chu in tibetan they call
it
Chu
uh they say if you eat a whole doughnut
for example there would be a few drops
of JW okay by the end of the process of
chewing swallowing
digesting like 95% of the doughnut would
be passed out of the body as waste and
then 5% is is kept inside the body as as
uh they call tongma into Buton it means
a a a clear essential nutritive essence
of food which your body has to refine
from gross food it has to chew it has to
swallow it has to burn it has to
separate and then finally it sends waste
out and it and it brings and this is
accomplished by the samay okay uh equal
wind
okay in the fourth month that triggers
uh say udana
vus udana means inbet it's called Uh G
gen uh upward clearing upward carrying
wind upward wind okay udana means upward
upward carrying wind upward traveling
wind
okay this wind is necessary for
breathing uh for speaking and for
drinking and eating it has to do with
the upper part of the body moving things
to the upper part of the body
okay uh in the fifth month the udana V
triggers the Viana V say vi
v in tibetan vi v is called
say yeaha means covers the whole body
this this this wind covers the whole
body all right and it enables
uh into they say enables the movement of
the limbs arms and hands it enables the
body it enables you to walk for example
coordination of walking uh and the and
the outer functions of the body
okay so these are the five uh major
winds in the body two of them are
important for a yogi the first two are
very important for a yogi okay what are
they called in Sanskrit pranu and aanu
okay pranav which holds the life in the
upper part of the body and then a
panu which is responsible for uh
elimination uh and also for retention of
when you retain urine or you retain seen
then that's also done with the
aanav and in some uh presentations of
yoga yoga is explained as a union right
uh yoga me means
Union the word jugular came from Yo Yu
the root of the word yoga and it means
the The Vessel the blood vessel which
connects the head to the body right it's
called the jugular vein so that came
from and the word yoke and the word
Union itself came from the same Roots
hug uh which means to join together so
some some yogic texts in both the Hindu
and Buddhist Traditions say that the
union of yoga refers to the union of the
downward wind with the life wind the
wind the primary wind in the upper part
of the body is joined or United With the
Wind of the lower part of the body
okay and it goes like this they say that
the the downward wind is going down
because it didn't have a choice it
didn't want to go down okay the downward
clearing wind would have preferred to
move up and down
but
block block huh block it was blocked
by the knot created by the two side
channels okay like that value that
energy was meant to travel through the
whole body and it was relegated to
downward elimination of things by a
problem in the body okay the elimination
of waste from the body and the and the
and the
existence of waste in the the body was
created by the blockage at the heart
okay it it it doesn't allow the downward
clearing Wind Free Passage through the
central Channel and so the downward wind
got stuck being the garbage man okay the
payu got stuck with this job of like
okay uh here's the waste of the body and
you you have to try you have to take out
the garbage every all the a couple times
a day all right that's your job okay and
then uh
pravu uh got stuck in the upper part of
the body it would also rather pass
freely up and down the central Channel
okay but it is blocked by the blockage
at the heart Channel
okay the the you have to distinguish
between the nod at the heart Channel and
the chakra at the heart Channel okay
there's a grante which means a notot at
the heart Channel and then there's a
chakra chakra results from the knot okay
first there's a knot uh which is created
by the two side channels three times
around the heart right that is a knot it
tightens and then that creates the
opening of the channels out to the side
from the area of the heart which is the
heart chakra okay the
the the appearance of additional
channels at the heart moving
horizontally to New York Florida Texas
Iona California Oregon Canada and Maine
is the heart chakra okay and it's called
the chakra again because when you look
down the central Channel you see these
spokes radiating out and that and so it
was given the name of chakra okay so a
chakra results from a KN
okay and then the five winds have
resulted from the same
not and the the the job of the five
winds is to take care of the functions
of the body breathing eating swallowing
digesting uh blood circulation uh what
do you call
it lymphatic lymphatic it's other word
anyway lymphatic system it's all of
these functions
are
miraculously uh carried out by the
vus because they were
blocked okay because they couldn't do
what they were supposed to do do all
right and those things which you think
oh this is miraculous my body is
circulating blood my body is breathing
my lymph is Flowing my body is digesting
my body is so smart to poop and peeee
you know what I mean now you're like oh
this is a miracle of you know of life
it's all a
mistake and it's all it's all deadly and
it makes your body mortal and it will
kill you okay the functions of the body
necessitated by the the knot at the
heart will kill you okay the blood
cannot
circulate uh endlessly it will stop it
it wears out okay the the uh elimination
of feces will end and and your own feces
will kill you the toxins in your own
poop will kill you you your body will
lose its ability to eliminate the waste
in the body all of these functions are
not functions of Life they are functions
of death okay the vus are killing you
you see and they were created by the
blockage at your heart all right they
were created by the nod at your heart
and that's created by what in the end
what what strengthens the side channels
to choke your
heart Starbucks and
traffic right ID and
Binga really okay it's your
emotions killing you okay your emotions
are responsible for your
mortality okay uh it's a it's a sad
thing all right all of the functions of
the body which are carried out by the
vus which are functions of Prana are all
being are all necessitated by the
blockage of at the
heart uh of the central Channel which
was which itself is caused by
your by your negative emotions you every
time you get angry every time you want
something that you don't really need you
are shortening your life okay and you
were born that way you were born for
that the structure of your heart chakra
you were hardwired to die you see you
are hardwired to be
mortal uh from in the womb okay the the
the structure of the heart chakra in the
womb already made you mortal you see and
and and the the point of uh yoga is to
reverse that situation okay the point
of the reason we're here and the reason
we're talking and the reason we're
studying is can you reverse the
situation can you open the heart chakra
see if you could open the heart chakra
then all of those virus would would flow
freely okay when they flow freely The
Way They Were Meant to in the first
place you have a perception of billions
upon billions of people and you love
them you see you're reversing whole
process from Starbucks to traffic to
choking at the heart to the to the
urination and the feces and the coughing
and the speaking and the blood
circulation all the Mortal functions the
functions of mortality if you can
release the side
channels uh if you can open the heart
chakra mentally you reach return to your
normal state which is
omniscience okay mentally you return to
high state of compassion and the ability
to serve all living beings at the same
moment you see that's your that's your
real nature and it's and it's it's you
are prevented you are held back from it
by your heart chck by the KN at your
heart okay so the exercise of releasing
the KN at the heart as the
pinga pingala and the AA are released
they actually then they then what you
call liia in in the yogic tradition they
they
withdraw the pinga and the ID are
withdraw into the central Channel they
go away they Wither in in Tibet they say
tiing oring CH it means the
vines die and wither and then you get
abati see Abad means throw off the two
Vines and Destroy them and it's a name
for the central Channel okay it's one of
the names for the middle Channel and
then you just become a a middle
Channel and there's no more five Valu
because there's nothing more to
eliminate you don't have faces you don't
need to breathe okay it's very beautiful
when the heart chakra is loosened how do
you know when you're getting close Okay
how will you know when you're getting
close to the heart chakra loosening you
will no longer need the for example
respiration it's no longer necessary
okay then uh a
panav comes up against pranav in the
heart chakra and there's a new kind of
balance there's a new kind of uh balance
between the two forces and then it's no
longer necessary to breathe okay and
then that has a name in the yogic uh
tradition right right which is
what yeah K kumaka say
kevala kumaka kumaka so kumaka means to
hold your breath right retain the breath
and you go you know people
go you know and they see how long how
many heartbeats can I hold the breath
it's a good way to get a headache and
it's a good way to get U slung which is
a Prana disorder and then you'll get oh
like this you know and you'll feel
nervous and you'll be grumpy all the
time okay uh slightly retentions are
very important okay slight retentions
when the aanav is able to rise the way
it was meant to and when the pranav is
able to descend the way it is meant to
then at the heart there's a state of
balance inside a thing called the
indestructible drop which we'll get to
after the
break okay cuz I don't want to overload
you but we only have like another hour
okay uh okay
but when there's a balance balance then
the breath stops okay naturally no
effort okay Keva means uh effortlessly
simple suspension of the breath and you
don't need to breathe see breathing is a
hassle and breathing is a sign that
you're IM mortal and it will kill you
the active breathing will kill you your
body cannot sustain breathing
indefinitely it will wear out okay it's
it has a limited amount of energy
there's only so many breaths you can
take in life okay we need to get to a
place where breath is no longer
necessary okay and that's that's when
the heart chakra is open so a lot of
cool things are happening to you if you
can open the heart chakra you have this
experience of of ultimate love right by
the way before that is a much more
important experience which we haven't
been talking about which is the direct
perception of Ultimate
Reality but then also your body starts
to change and your body goes back to its
natural condition which which is light
then the body is no longer made of Flesh
okay and it's not what do you
call subject to the visites of Flesh you
see you no
longer your body no longer has to worry
about pooping and urinating and eating
and breathing okay then your body is in
its natural condition I don't know I
think life would be kind of boring if I
didn't have to eat but I think you could
still make I'm working through jul a
child personally uh
I'm making my llama like one meal you
know every couple weeks from Julian
child I think I will still do it and
just serve it you know and they can look
at it and then we can throw it away or
something you know uh but uh you
wouldn't have to eat anymore you see you
would be
the you would become a body of Light
which you need to have if you want to
help a lot of people because only a body
of light can be split at will into
billions of bodies okay so to to really
be of service to
people you have to stop the five bias by
opening the heart chakra and stopping
all this Mortal stuff okay mortality
stuff it's a beautiful thing okay to
open the heart chakra is a beautiful
thing right so that's how the Prana and
the vi relates to opening the heart
chakra all right um